

Salman Shah

Ph.D (pursuing)

No.8, Kokilam St., Taramani, Chennai-600042

Contact No.: +91 9946 060 177 E-mail: salman.shamsu@gmail.com Webpage: salman-iitm.github.io/

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Experienced professional with a solid foundation in both experimental and theoretical fluid mechanics. Proficient in utilizing advanced analytical and computational methods to analyze complex fluid flow phenomena and validate experimental data. Demonstrated expertise as a researcher, mentor, and model designer within academic and professional settings.

EDUCATION

Ph.D - Ocean Engineering

India Institute of Technology Madras Tamil Nadu, India

2023 - Present

CGPA - 9.24

M. Tech - Thermal Engineering

Cochin University of Science and Technology Kerala, India CGPA - 9.06

2019 - 2021

• B. Tech - Mechanical Engineering

A.P.L. Abdul Kalam Technological University Kerala, India

2015 - 2019

CGPA - 8.78

EXPERIENCE

Assistant Professor - Dept. of Mechanical Engg. Sree Narayana Gurukulam College of Engineering, Ernakulam, Kerala

2021 - 2023

Courses instructed: Mechanics of Fluids, Fluid Mechanics and Hydraulic Machines lab, Thermodynamics, etc.

Add-on courses mentored - Ansys FLUENT and Autodesk Inventor

Additional Responsibilities - Asst. Program officer - NSS UNIT 569, Head of Nature Club, Staff advisor

 CFD Expert, Designer and Mentor KrewX Edtech LLP, Part time

2020 - 2022

Key responsibilities: Design engineering solutions, Simulation and post processing, Mentoring

Domain: Fluid-Structure interaction, Thermal analysis

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Experience with numerical method, data analysis, interpretation and documentation BEM, MATLAB, LaTeX
- Proficient in conducting physical model tests

Wave Flume, Wave basin tests on fixed/floating structures

• Proficient with tool based analysis

Ansys-AQWA, Fluent, Orcaflex

Skilled in delivering research presentations with clarity, visual impact, and audience engagement

Salman Shah

salman.shamsu@gmail.com

PUBLICATIONS

- Published abstract: "Effect of Spatial Distribution of Sinker Arrays on Volume Deformation in Offshore Aquaculture cages".
 Volume of abstracts, WOSC, NIOT 2024
- A Numerical Investigation on Flow Characteristics of Jets Emerging from a Multi-Lobed Nozzle with Pointed Corrugations. International Journal of Applied Engineering Research ISSN 0973-4562 Volume 18, Number 1 (2023) pp. 17-20.

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

- Effect of Spatial Distribution of Sinker Arrays on Volume Deformation in Offshore Aquaculture Cages
- Determination of Operational Limit for a Conduction Cooled 6U Versa Module Eurocard
- Smart Carro: A motorised wheel barrow

COMPLEMENTARY PROFESSIONAL INVOLVEMENT

- Internship on AC systems-functions Automotive Battery service, BOSCH
- Internship in Foundry unit of Steel Industries Kerala Limited, Palakkad
- Workshop on Vibration measurement and analysis, Industry Institute Interaction Cell, SOE, CUSAT
- Attended FDP,s on "Outcome Based Education" and "Nanotechnology in engineering for a Sustainable future"

ACHIEVEMENTS AND AWARDS

- Presented an article in World Ocean Science Congress, 2014
- Presented a Paper in International Conference on Machine Intelligence in Research and Development-accepted for publication
- Secured 2nd Rank From Cochin University of Science and Technology in Masters- Thermal Engineering
- Successfully completed Masters project at NPOL, Kochi
- Project SMART CARRO bagged first runner up in Mechanical Project Expo Organised by Christ College Irinjalakkuda
- Branchwise College Topper, Mechanical Engineering
- Got selected to DISHA, a unit under National Service Scheme for public services
- Bagged best outgoing student award- High School and Higher secondary school